<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-08T19:45:07+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ngozi Nwogwugwu</title><subtitle>nwogwugwu.eth</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Notes: Operating Systems Overview</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/programming/operating-systems-overview/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes: Operating Systems Overview" /><published>2022-07-07T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2022-07-07T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/programming/Operating-Systems-Overview</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/programming/operating-systems-overview/">&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://codex.cs.yale.edu/avi/os-book/OS10/index.html&quot;&gt;Operating System Concepts&lt;/a&gt; by Avi Silberschatz, Peter Baer Galvin, Greg Gagne (Chapter 1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;Operating System&lt;/strong&gt; is software that manages a computer’s hardware&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provides basis for application programs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;acts as intermediary between user and hardware&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allocates resources to computer programs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-operating-systems-do&quot;&gt;What Operating Systems Do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Components to a computer system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hardware&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;operating system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;application systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;user&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;system-view&quot;&gt;System View&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;from a computer’s point of view, the OS is the program most intimately involved with the hardware. It’s a &lt;strong&gt;resource allocator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;control program&lt;/strong&gt; manages the execution of user programs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prevents improper use of the computer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;defining-operating-systems&quot;&gt;Defining Operating Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can be defined as a combination of the kernel and system programs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the kernel&lt;/strong&gt;: the operating system is the one program that’s always running. This is one possible definition of an operating system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;system programs:&lt;/strong&gt; associated with the operating system, but not part of the kernel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;middleware:&lt;/strong&gt; a set of software frameworks that provide additional services to application developers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;computer-system-organization&quot;&gt;Computer-System Organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;interrupts&quot;&gt;Interrupts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interrupt is a signal from the hardware to the CPU, usually by the system bus, which causes the CPU to stop what it’s doing and transfer execution to a fixed location. These locations could be hardcoded, or stored in a table of pointers called the &lt;strong&gt;interrupt vector&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;storage-structure&quot;&gt;Storage Structure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers run most of their programs from main memory (or &lt;strong&gt;RAM&lt;/strong&gt;), which is volatile. You have to load the program to main memory beforehand&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DRAM:&lt;/strong&gt; Dynamic Random-Access Memory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bootstrap Program&lt;/strong&gt; - the first program to run on a computer. Uses firmware storage to store the program, since RAM is volatile&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t store programs in main memory for two reasons&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main memory is too small to store all our programs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Main memory is volatile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;io-structure&quot;&gt;I/O Structure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Operating systems handle I/O&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;computer-system-architecture&quot;&gt;Computer-System Architecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are single processor systems and multi processor systems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;core&lt;/strong&gt; - the component that executes instructions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;multiprocessor-systems&quot;&gt;Multiprocessor systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;have processors that share resources (clock, memory, etc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Primary advantage: increased throughput&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disadvantage: One processor could sit idle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multicore Systems&lt;/strong&gt; - have multiple cores on a single chip (for faster communication)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clustered-systems&quot;&gt;Clustered Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;composed of two more more &lt;strong&gt;nodes&lt;/strong&gt; (individual systems) that are loosely coupled&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;redundancy leads to high availability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Parallelization&lt;/strong&gt; - a technique which divides a program into separate components so they can be run in parallel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;operating-system-operations&quot;&gt;Operating System Operations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;system daemons&lt;/strong&gt; programs that are loaded into memory at boot time. Services that are provided outside of the kernel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;multiprogramming-and-multitasking&quot;&gt;Multiprogramming and Multitasking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multiprogramming&lt;/strong&gt; increases CPU utilization by keeping several processes in memory simultaneously. Gives processing time to a new program when the current program is idle&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multitasking&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;-&lt;/strong&gt; when the CPU switches between programs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dual-mode-and-multi-mode-operation&quot;&gt;Dual-Mode and Multi-Mode Operation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers must distinguish between operating-system code and user-defined code. This prevents misuse of the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To implement this, we need two &lt;strong&gt;modes of operation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kernel mode (AKA supervisor mode, system mode, privileged mode)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;user mode&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mode bit&lt;/strong&gt; - indicates the current mode, added to the hardware of the computer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;timer&quot;&gt;Timer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a timer can be set to interrupt the computer after a specified period&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;resource-management&quot;&gt;Resource Management&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;operating-system-structures&quot;&gt;Operating-System Structures&lt;/h1&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">source: Operating System Concepts by Avi Silberschatz, Peter Baer Galvin, Greg Gagne (Chapter 1)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes: Stream Processing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/programming/ddia-stream-processing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes: Stream Processing" /><published>2022-07-07T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2022-07-07T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/programming/DDIA-Stream-Processing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/programming/ddia-stream-processing/">&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/designing-data-intensive-applications/9781491903063/&quot;&gt;Designing Data Intensive Applications&lt;/a&gt; by Martin Kleppmann (Chapter 11)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of data is unbounded - it arrives gradually over time. Processing unbounded data in batches might not make sense in every situation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stream Processing&lt;/strong&gt; - run processing continuously. Alternative to batch processing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;event streams&lt;/strong&gt; - data made incrementally available over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;transmitting-event-streams&quot;&gt;Transmitting Event Streams&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;event&lt;/strong&gt; - small, self-contained immutable object. Contains the details for something that happened at some point in time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can be encoded&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;producer (publisher)&lt;/strong&gt; generates events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;consumers (subscribers)&lt;/strong&gt; process events&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;topic&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;(stream)&lt;/strong&gt; a group of related events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;messaging-systems&quot;&gt;Messaging Systems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;strong&gt;messaging system&lt;/strong&gt;, producers send events to consumers. In a &lt;strong&gt;publish/subscribe model&lt;/strong&gt;, we can have multiple producers and consumers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one or more &lt;strong&gt;producers&lt;/strong&gt; sends a message with an event to a &lt;strong&gt;topic&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the message gets pushed to one or more consumers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solutions to cases where consumers aren’t fast enough to process all of the messages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;drop messages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;buffer messages in a queue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;apply &lt;strong&gt;backpressure&lt;/strong&gt; (blocking producer from sending messages)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;direct-messaging-from-producers-to-consumers&quot;&gt;Direct messaging from producers to consumers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;possibility of message loss, and there’s no recovering data if a consumer goes offline. Examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UDP multicast (finance)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;brokerless messaging libraries (ZeroMQ)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;message-brokers&quot;&gt;Message brokers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a database - optimized for handling event streams&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better fault tolerance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consumers are async&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;message-brokers-compared-to-databases&quot;&gt;Message brokers compared to databases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;message brokers automatically delete messages once they get consumed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;topics are analogous to DB indexes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;message brokers don’t support arbitrary queries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;multiple-consumers&quot;&gt;Multiple consumers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;load balancing&lt;/strong&gt; - each message gets delivered to one consumer. Allows for parallel processing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;fan out&lt;/strong&gt; - each message is delivered to all consumers. Allows different consumers to process the same data in different ways&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;acknowledgement-and-redelivery&quot;&gt;Acknowledgement and redelivery&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a broker will only delete a message from its queue if it gets an ack from the consumer. If the consumer consumes the message, then breaks before it can send the ack, the broker will send the message to another consumer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can lead to messages being processed out of order. One way to avoid this issue is to route all related messages to a single consumer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;partitioned-logs&quot;&gt;Partitioned Logs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;log-based message brokers&lt;/strong&gt; are a hybrid of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;databases (durable storage) - this means that messages don’t get deleted when consumers process them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;messaging - means low-latency notifications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-logs-for-message-storage&quot;&gt;Using logs for message storage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A log is an &lt;strong&gt;append-only sequence of records&lt;/strong&gt; on disk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we can use this for message brokers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;these logs can be partitioned&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;each partition has an &lt;strong&gt;offset&lt;/strong&gt; for every message. These are ordered within a partition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;products: Kafka, Amazon Kenesis, DistributedLog&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;logs-compared-to-traditional-messaging&quot;&gt;Logs compared to traditional messaging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No need for fan-out messaging, since each consumer can read the log independently&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A consumer consumes &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the logs for a specific topic. Downsides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;max num nodes for a topic is the number of the topic’s log partition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;slow messages can cause lags for all the subsequent messages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;consumer-offsets&quot;&gt;Consumer Offsets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consumers pay attention to message offsets as they work through a log&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;disk-space-usage&quot;&gt;Disk space usage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We don’t have infinite disk space. One way to deal with this is to delete expired data as the log gets too big&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;circular buffer&lt;/strong&gt; - bounded-size buffer that deletes old messages when it gets full&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;when-consumers-cant-keep-up-with-producers&quot;&gt;When consumers can’t keep up with producers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;options: drop messages, buffer, apply backpressure&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;it’s normal to monitor consumers to make sure they don’t get too far behind&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;one advantage to partitioned logs: if one consumer falls behind, it doesn’t affect the others in any way&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;replaying-old-messages&quot;&gt;Replaying old messages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to replay old messages, just reset the consumer offset. The message broker doesn’t know anything about the offset, so it won’t affect anything else&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;databases-and-streams&quot;&gt;Databases and Streams&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;there’s a fundamental connection between databases and streams&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keeping-systems-in-sync&quot;&gt;Keeping Systems in Sync&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;related (or replicated) data in different locations needs to be kept in sync. Some possible solutions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dual writes&lt;/strong&gt; write to both systems at once - we get problems if one fails while the other succeeds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;periodic database dumps - downside is that there’s high latency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;change-data-capture-cdc&quot;&gt;Change Data Capture (CDC)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the process of observing all data changes written to a database and extracting those changes in a form that is readable to other systems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;implementing-change-data-capture&quot;&gt;Implementing change data capture&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;derived data systems&lt;/strong&gt; log consumers for CDC&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you can use DB triggers to implement CDC, but this is fragile&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDC is usually async, so you have to keep in mind that there might be lag&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;initial-snapshot&quot;&gt;Initial snapshot&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a DB snapshot should correspond to a known position in the change log&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;log-compaction&quot;&gt;Log compaction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;throw away duplicate logs to free up space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if a key is frequently overwritten, garbage-collect old values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;event-sourcing&quot;&gt;Event Sourcing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;technique: store all the changes to the application state as a log of events&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developed by the domain-driven design community&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;application logic is built on immutable events written to a log (append only)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Deriving current state from the event log&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications that use event sources should be able to take a stream of events and turn it into an application state&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Log compaction isn’t possible with event sourcing (as opposed to CDC) because events are modeled on a higher level&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;commands-and-events&quot;&gt;Commands and events&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;command&lt;/strong&gt; is a request when it first arrives. Once that requests gets saved, it’s considered an &lt;strong&gt;event&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;once a command becomes an event, it’s in the app’s history&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;command validation should happen asynchronously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;state-streams-and-immutability&quot;&gt;State, Streams and Immutability&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a math-y way of thinking about this is that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$state(now) = \int_{t=0}^{now}stream(t)dt$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;$stream(t) = {d state(t)}/dt$&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;advantages-of-immutable-events&quot;&gt;advantages of immutable events&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;auditability - data is never deleted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more information - you have an app’s entire history&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;deriving-several-views-from-the-same-event-log&quot;&gt;Deriving several views from the same event log&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use the same data for different features&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;one advantage of keeping the event log around is that you can use it if you want to develop a new feature. The new feature has the entire history of the app’s events, so it’s up to date immediately&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Command Query Responsibility Segregation&lt;/strong&gt; - you get flexibility by separating write data from read data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;concurrency-control&quot;&gt;Concurrency control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;event sourcing means async processes, which mean lag&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if this is a problem, you might want to wrap log writes and reads in a transaction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;limitations-of-immutability&quot;&gt;Limitations of immutability&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you run out of space&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you might &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to delete some logs - it’s hard when the information is scattered all over the place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;processing-streams&quot;&gt;Processing Streams&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;operator (job)&lt;/strong&gt; piece of code that processes streams. It has three options for processing streams:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Save to DB&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Push the events to a user&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Process stream to make an output stream
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;option to combine it with other data sources, including other streams&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stream processors can be run in parallel on partitioned streams. This is similar to MapReduce dataflow engines - transforming and filtering records works the same&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stream processing never ends, so some things don’t make sense to do in stream processing (like sorting)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;uses-of-stream-processing&quot;&gt;Uses of Stream Processing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;used to just be monitoring, but we have more use cases now&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;complex-event-processing&quot;&gt;complex event processing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;use a query language to describe a pattern of events to look for. When the processor sees a sequence of events that match, it emits a &lt;strong&gt;complex event&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stream-analytics&quot;&gt;stream analytics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;aggregations and statistical metrics over a large number of events&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;usually computed over fixed time intervals (&lt;strong&gt;windows&lt;/strong&gt;)
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;maintaining-materialized-views&quot;&gt;Maintaining materialized views&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;materialized view&lt;/strong&gt; - an alternate view of a dataset&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can be queried more efficiently&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;updates when the underlying data changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need all events to make a materialized view&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;search-of-streams&quot;&gt;Search of streams&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you search a stream (for something like string matching), you have to store it first&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reasoning-about-time&quot;&gt;Reasoning about time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this is hard, but most frameworks use the clock on the processing machine (&lt;strong&gt;processing time&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you run into problems if there’s a lot of lag
    &lt;h3 id=&quot;event-time-vs-processing-time&quot;&gt;Event time vs processing time&lt;/h3&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;it’s important to model these as distinct, especially in situations where there’s some lag&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;knowing-when-youre-ready&quot;&gt;Knowing when you’re ready&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can’t be sure when all events for a particular window have been delivered&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;unless all the publishers publish events that say “no more events for this time window”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ways to handle stragglers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ignore them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;publish a correction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;which-clock-do-you-use&quot;&gt;Which clock do you use&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;three possible timestamps:
    1. time the event happened
    2. time the event was sent
    3. time the event was received by the server&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;types-of-windows&quot;&gt;Types of windows&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;tumbling window&lt;/strong&gt; - fixed length, every event belongs to exactly one window&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;hopping window&lt;/strong&gt; - fixed length, allows for windows to overlap a little&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sliding window&lt;/strong&gt; - fixed length, contains events that happen within some interval of each other&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;session window&lt;/strong&gt; - no fixed duration, just group all the events that  happened close together in time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;stream-joins&quot;&gt;Stream Joins&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joining data on a stream is challenging because new events can appear any time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stream-stream-join-window-join&quot;&gt;Stream-stream join (window join)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;challenge: the two events might happen far apart from each other&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you’ll have to save the first event in memory. You have to save &lt;strong&gt;state&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stream-table-join-stream-enrichment&quot;&gt;Stream-table join (stream enrichment)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for each event, query the DB&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;helps, because you can query old data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to reduce roundtrip time, it might help to keep a copy of the DB on the processor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;table-table-join-materialized-view-maintenance&quot;&gt;Table-table join (materialized view maintenance)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keep a cache of events, if they’re too expensive to push to the DB immediately&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-dependence-of-joins&quot;&gt;Time-dependence of joins&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The order of events is important, if they depend on each other&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fault-tolerance&quot;&gt;Fault Tolerance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with streams, you can’t wait for the processing to end before you make the results visible (because it’s infinite)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;microbatching-and-checkpointing&quot;&gt;Microbatching and checkpointing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just make a batch out of one second of data and process it right away. Save the data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your stream operator crashes, it can just start from the most recent saved data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;atomic-commits&quot;&gt;Atomic commits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wrap processing and side effects in a transaction. We don’t want side effects to happen if the processing fails&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;idempotence&quot;&gt;Idempotence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you can perform an operation multiple times, and it has the same effect as if it was performed one time&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">source: Designing Data Intensive Applications by Martin Kleppmann (Chapter 11)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes: Kafka Producers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/programming/kafka-producers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes: Kafka Producers" /><published>2022-07-03T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2022-07-03T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/programming/Kafka-Producers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/programming/kafka-producers/">&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/kafka-the-definitive/9781491936153//&quot;&gt;Kafka: The Definitive Guide&lt;/a&gt; by Neha Narkhede, Gwen Shapira, Todd Palino (Chapter 3)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Producers write messages to Kafka&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;you can use the built-in API or use a third party one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ProducerRecord -&lt;/strong&gt; A key/value pair to be sent to Kafka&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;includes (required) &lt;strong&gt;topic name&lt;/strong&gt;, an (optional) &lt;strong&gt;partition number&lt;/strong&gt;, and an (optional) &lt;strong&gt;key and value&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;producer&lt;/strong&gt; serializes the key and value objects into ByteArrays, then sends it to a &lt;strong&gt;partitioner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it adds the record to a &lt;strong&gt;batch of records&lt;/strong&gt;. All these records will be sent to the same topic and partition&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a separate thread actually sends the batches to the right Kafka brokers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;broker&lt;/strong&gt; acks when it gets the messages&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;serializers&quot;&gt;Serializers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kafka includes serializers for integers and byteArrays by default, but that doesn’t cover other types. It’s recommend that people use a generic serialization library (like Protobuf)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;partitions&quot;&gt;Partitions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kafka uses a message’s &lt;strong&gt;keys&lt;/strong&gt; to determine which topic partition to put the message into&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you don’t include a key, the producer will chose a partition at random (round robin)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you do include a key, the producer hashes it and maps the hash to a partition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the partition depends on the key:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can use this information to optimize your application&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if the partition is unavailable, you’ll get an error&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;once you add more partitions, Kafka can’t guarantee that messages map to partitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">source: Kafka: The Definitive Guide by Neha Narkhede, Gwen Shapira, Todd Palino (Chapter 3)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes: Kafka Introduction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/programming/kafka-introduction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes: Kafka Introduction" /><published>2022-06-03T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2022-06-03T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/programming/Kafka-Introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/programming/kafka-introduction/">&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/kafka-the-definitive/9781491936153//&quot;&gt;Kafka: The Definitive Guide&lt;/a&gt; by Neha Narkhede, Gwen Shapira, Todd Palino (Chapter 1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;publishsubscribe-messaging&quot;&gt;Publish/Subscribe Messaging&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;message&lt;/strong&gt; - a base unit of information. Often has a category&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;publisher&lt;/strong&gt; - sends and classifies messages, but does not direct them anywhere&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;subscriber&lt;/strong&gt; - receives certain classes of messages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;broker&lt;/strong&gt; - central point where messages are published to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;enter-kafka&quot;&gt;Enter Kafka&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a “distributed commit log”, or a “distributed streaming platform”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed to store data &lt;em&gt;durably&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;in order&lt;/em&gt;. This means that it can be read deterministically&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another key feature of Kafka is that the &lt;em&gt;data is distributed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;messages-and-batches&quot;&gt;Messages and Batches&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;message&lt;/strong&gt; - unit of data within Kafka. Kafka has no knowledge about the content of the message&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;key&lt;/strong&gt; - an optional component of a message. Used to control how messages are written to partition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;batch&lt;/strong&gt; - collection of messages being produced to the same topic and partition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;larger batches lead to messages being handled more efficiently, but individual messages take longer to propagate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;schemas&quot;&gt;Schemas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optional, but recommended. Allow engineers to decouple writing and reading messages&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;human-readable schemas (JSON, XML) lack type handling and schema versions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;alternatives, like &lt;strong&gt;Apache Avro&lt;/strong&gt;, have compact serialization formats, type handling and separate schemas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;topics--partitions&quot;&gt;Topics &amp;amp; Partitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;topics&lt;/strong&gt; - how messages in Kafka are organized. Can be broken down into partitions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;partitions&lt;/strong&gt; - a single log that messages are appended to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can be hosted on different servers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;time ordering is guaranteed within a partition but not a topic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;stream&lt;/strong&gt; - represent data moving from the producers to consumers for a given topic&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;producers--consumers&quot;&gt;Producers &amp;amp; Consumers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kafka clients can be users or consumers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kafka Connect API - advanced client API for data integration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Kafka Streams - for stream processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;producers&quot;&gt;producers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;create new messages. Generally publish messages to specific topics and usually don’t care which partition the message goes to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;consumers&quot;&gt;consumers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;consume messages. Can be subscribed to one or more topics, reads messages in order&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;offset&lt;/strong&gt; - metadata (a counter) given to each message within a partition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a consumer will use this to keep track of which messages it’s already consumed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;consumer group&lt;/strong&gt; - a set of consumers reading from a topic. Each partition is read by a single consumer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ownership&lt;/strong&gt; - mapping of a consumer to a partition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brokers--clusters&quot;&gt;Brokers &amp;amp; Clusters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;broker&lt;/strong&gt; is a single Kafka server&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it receives messages from producers, assigns offsets to them, and commits them to disk&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;services fetch requests from consumers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;owns a partition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;cluster&lt;/strong&gt; is a group of brokers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;controller&lt;/strong&gt; is responsible for administrative operations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A broker that is the &lt;strong&gt;leader&lt;/strong&gt; of a partition is responsible for receiving messages from producers and for replicating the partition to other brokers in its cluster&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;retention&lt;/strong&gt; - durable storage of messages&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can be for a period of time &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; dictated by a data limit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;expired messages are deleted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;multiple-clusters&quot;&gt;Multiple Clusters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might want multiple clusters for&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data segregation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;security isolation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;redundancy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mirror Maker&lt;/strong&gt; - like a mega-kafka. Messages are consumed from one cluster and produced for another&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-kafka&quot;&gt;Why Kafka?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;multiple producers and consumers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data is easy to retain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;scalable and performant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-cases-for-kafka&quot;&gt;Use Cases for Kafka&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;activity tracking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;messaging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;metrics &amp;amp; logging&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;stream processing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;kafkas-origin&quot;&gt;Kafka’s Origin&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;created at LinkedIn to address a data pipeline problem&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;released as an open source project on GitHub in 2010&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s named after Franz Kafka, but for no particular reason. Just because it sounded cool&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">source: Kafka: The Definitive Guide by Neha Narkhede, Gwen Shapira, Todd Palino (Chapter 1)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Fitness RPG</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/programming/fitness-rpg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Fitness RPG" /><published>2022-05-01T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2022-05-01T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/programming/my-fitness-rpg</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/programming/fitness-rpg/">&lt;p&gt;I made a simple phone game that draws on fitness stats from your wearable. The game’s concept is quite simple: Fight monsters to gain experience points and gold, while using real-life factors to determine its behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fitness stats like cardiovascular strain and sleep determine a character’s strength and health. Other real-world factors, such as current weather and moon phase, determine which monsters appear. By using mundane events in the real world to create fun game mechanics, I hope to encourage my players to view daily life with a layer of whimsey. Naturally, this would also encourage players to form better habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://witch-game-text-adventure-i26wf.ondigitalocean.app/&quot;&gt;I published a demo. Try it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/witch_game/IMG_9150.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_9150.PNG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/witch_game/IMG_9151.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_9151.PNG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/witch_game/IMG_9152.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_9152.PNG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/witch_game/IMG_9153.PNG&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_9153.PNG&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-did-i-make-this&quot;&gt;How did I make this?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tech stack I used for this is quite straightforward. I used &lt;strong&gt;PostgreSQL&lt;/strong&gt; to store data and &lt;strong&gt;Django&lt;/strong&gt; to create the REST API. I chose &lt;strong&gt;Expo/ReactNative&lt;/strong&gt; to generate a mobile-friendly frontend as I wanted the option to publish my game as an iOS app. Lastly, I decided to use  &lt;strong&gt;DigitalOcean&lt;/strong&gt; to host the entire app because it was fairly straightforward to set up automated deployment for the frontend and the backend of my project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aspirations&quot;&gt;Aspirations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to pull in more real-time data, such as user location or meditation minutes. Additionally, I want to make the gameplay more complex, and use a storyline and art to make the game more compelling. I would also consider adding NFT items as a way for the game to generate profit. A player could pay to mint a weapon, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learnings&quot;&gt;Learnings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I view the current incarnation of this game as a proof-of-concept, and I learned quite a bit while building this version of the game. Here’s what I’ll do for my next version:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deploy early and often&lt;/strong&gt; - I want to publish a live version of my game as early as possible so I can get feedback at every step of development.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start with the integrations&lt;/strong&gt; - I’m moving from Whoop to Apple Health, since Apple Health has far more users and allows for developer integration.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Web is okay!&lt;/strong&gt; - Getting published on the App Store is a whole thing. I want immediate feedback on my app, so I’ll publish my game to the web before I focus on creating an iOS app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I made a simple phone game that draws on fitness stats from your wearable. The game’s concept is quite simple: Fight monsters to gain experience points and gold, while using real-life factors to determine its behavior.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes: Writing Smart Contracts</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/programming/cryptozombies/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes: Writing Smart Contracts" /><published>2022-01-17T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2022-01-17T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/programming/cryptozombies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/programming/cryptozombies/">&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cryptozombies.io/&quot;&gt;CryptoZombies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cryptozombies&quot;&gt;CryptoZombies&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cryptozombies.io/en/lesson/1/chapter/1&quot;&gt;https://cryptozombies.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;make-a-zombie-factory&quot;&gt;make a zombie factory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goal--pragma&quot;&gt;goal &amp;amp; pragma&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;requirements for a zombie factory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;database with all zombies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;function to create zombies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;each zombie will be unique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;zombie dna&lt;/strong&gt; represented as an int. Different parts of the int map to different zombie traits&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a &lt;strong&gt;contract&lt;/strong&gt; is the fundamental building block of ethereum applications&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all variables and functions belong to a contract&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;solidarity&lt;/strong&gt; object oriented programming language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;version pragma&lt;/strong&gt; declaration of the version for the compiler&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all solidarity code starts with this, prevents issues with future compiler versions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;example contract&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;pragma&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;solidity&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;contract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ZombieFactory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;variables-and-math&quot;&gt;variables and math&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;state variables&lt;/strong&gt; permanently stored in contract storage. They’re written to the blockchain, similar to writing to a database&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;uint&lt;/strong&gt; unsigned int, can’t be negative&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;math operations in solidity are pretty straightforward&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;structs--arrays&quot;&gt;structs &amp;amp; arrays&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;structs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Person&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;age&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;arrays&lt;/strong&gt; there are &lt;strong&gt;fixed&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;dynamic&lt;/strong&gt; arrays. To make an array dynamic, don’t specify the length. You can also create arrays out of structs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fixedArray&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dynamicArray&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Person&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;people&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if you create a dynamic array of structs, it gets stored in the blockchain. It’s like storing structured data in a database&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if you declare an array as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;public&lt;/code&gt;, solidity will create a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;getter&lt;/code&gt; method for it. Makes them readable but not writable by other contracts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you can &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;push&lt;/code&gt; structs and variables to arrays&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;functions&quot;&gt;functions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;functions&lt;/strong&gt; look like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;eatHamburgers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_amount&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sayHello&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;view&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;returns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; specifies the visibility of the function. Functions are public by default&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; functions are only visible by other functions within the contract. Private functions start with an underscore&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/code&gt; indicates that &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_name&lt;/code&gt; should be stored in memory. This is &lt;strong&gt;required for reference types&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;types of arguments&lt;/strong&gt; - you can pass them in &lt;strong&gt;by value&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;by reference&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any variable that you pass around by reference (arrays, strings, structs, mappings) vs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;any variable that you pass into the function. &lt;strong&gt;Changes to these variables are limited to the function&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;return values&lt;/strong&gt; - the function declaration contains the return value type&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;function modifiers&lt;/strong&gt; - a way to document the type of function you’re writing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;view&lt;/strong&gt; - it’s viewing data from the blockchain but not modifying it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;pure&lt;/strong&gt; - not even accessing data from the app&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-keccak256-to-create-a-random-zombie&quot;&gt;using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Keccak256&lt;/code&gt; to create a random zombie&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;keccak256&lt;/code&gt; is a hash function that outputs a 256-bit hex number&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;input of type bytes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;to pack a string into bytes&lt;/strong&gt; use the function &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;abi.encodePacked&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;code so far&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;pragma&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;solidity&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;contract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ZombieFactory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    
      &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// declare our event here
&lt;/span&gt;    
      &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dnaDigits&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dnaModulus&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;**&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dnaDigits&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;struct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Zombie&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dna&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    
      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Zombie&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;zombies&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_createZombie&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_dna&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;zombies&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;push&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Zombie&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_dna&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// and fire it here
&lt;/span&gt;      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_generateRandomDna&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;view&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;returns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rand&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;keccak256&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;abi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;encodePacked&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)));&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rand&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dnaModulus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    
      &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;createRandomZombie&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;randDna&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_generateRandomDna&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_createZombie&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;randDna&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;events&quot;&gt;events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;your contract can listen to &lt;strong&gt;events&lt;/strong&gt; on the blockchain and take an action&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-frontend&quot;&gt;the frontend&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethereum has a Javascript library called &lt;strong&gt;Web3.js&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;make-the-zombie-app-more-game&quot;&gt;Make the zombie app more game&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;addresses-and-mappings&quot;&gt;Addresses and Mappings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;accounts&lt;/strong&gt; similar to bank accounts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;owned by an individual or contract&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;holds a balance of &lt;strong&gt;ether&lt;/strong&gt;, can send or receive ether&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;addresses&lt;/strong&gt; hex identifiers for the accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;mappings&lt;/strong&gt; key-values stores. Defined like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;mapping&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;account&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;accountBalance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;msgsender&quot;&gt;msg.sender&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this function returns the address of whatever (person or contract) that called the current function&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;require&quot;&gt;require&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; makes the function throw an exception if some conditions are not met&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inheritance-and-import&quot;&gt;inheritance and import&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the syntax &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;contract descendentContract is ancestorContract {}&lt;/code&gt; will create an inherited contract&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the syntax &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;import &quot;./another_file.sol&quot;;&lt;/code&gt; will import a file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;storage-and-memory&quot;&gt;storage and memory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;storage&lt;/strong&gt; gets stored on the blockchain. This is analogous to writing to disk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;memory&lt;/strong&gt; variables in memory are temporary, and disappear when the function ends&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you include these as keywords when you declare variables&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;internal--external&quot;&gt;Internal &amp;amp; External&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;functions in solidity have different visibilities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;internal&lt;/code&gt; is the same as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;private&lt;/code&gt;, except it includes inherited classes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;external&lt;/code&gt; is like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;public&lt;/code&gt; - except &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;external&lt;/code&gt; functions are &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; accessible from outside the contract&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading-from-other-contracts&quot;&gt;reading from other contracts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we need to define an &lt;strong&gt;interface&lt;/strong&gt; to interact with other contracts. Interfaces look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;contract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;exampleInterface&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;otherFunction&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;inputVar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;view&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;returns&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cryptokitties&quot;&gt;cryptokitties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;source code is here (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dapperlabs/cryptokitties-bounty/blob/master/contracts/KittyCore.sol#L91&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we initialize the contract using the address of the contract&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;ethereum&quot;&gt;Ethereum&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethereum contracts are &lt;strong&gt;immutable&lt;/strong&gt;. This makes security a huge concern. Because of this, it make sense to have getters and setters for some contract variables, like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;setKittyContractAddress&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;constructors&lt;/strong&gt; - optional functions that get executed when an object gets created&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;function modieifer&lt;/strong&gt; modify other functions, usually to check some requirements before the execution (like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;onlyOwner&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;uses the keyword &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;modifier&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;uses &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_;&lt;/code&gt; - when this gets run, it jumps to the modified function&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ownable-contracts&quot;&gt;ownable contracts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to prevent randos from changing the contract, you make a contract &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ownable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;OpenZeppelin&lt;/code&gt; solidity library&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;has secure smart contracts that you can use in your own dapps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense to be careful with ownable contracts. The owners can add backdoors for themselves&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this means you should read code before you trust it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gas&quot;&gt;gas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;you can buy gas with ether&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;gas required to execute a function depends on the function’s complexity. This encourages code optimization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;struct-packing&quot;&gt;struct packing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solidity reserves 256 bits for all uints (8, 16, 32…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;exception&lt;/strong&gt;: inside of structs. You’ll want to use the smallest possible integer sub-types and cluster identically-typed fields&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time&quot;&gt;time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;now&lt;/code&gt; - built in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;days&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;months&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;minutes&lt;/code&gt; - you can say &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;now + 5 minutes&lt;/code&gt; to mean five minutes from now&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the &lt;strong&gt;2038 problem&lt;/strong&gt; - it will be so many seconds since 1970 that we’ll have overflows from a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;uint32&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;default is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;uint256&lt;/code&gt;, so we should cast dates to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;uint32&lt;/code&gt;s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;passing-references-to-structs&quot;&gt;passing references to structs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can pass a pointer to a struct in a function like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;myFunc&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;MyStruct&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;storage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_myStruct&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;function-modifiers-can-take-input-variables&quot;&gt;function modifiers can take input variables&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You declare them like any other function with input variables&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;modifier&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;olderThan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_age&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;User&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;storage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;require&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;age&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_age&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you’d input the variables in your function definition&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DrinkAlcohol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;User&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;storaage&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;olderThan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;_user&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gas--view-functions&quot;&gt;gas &amp;amp; view functions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you call a view function externally, it will just find the value on your local ethereum node. &lt;strong&gt;This does not cost you gas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;if you call a view function from &lt;em&gt;inside&lt;/em&gt; a contract, &lt;strong&gt;it will cost you gas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gas--building-variables-on-the-fly&quot;&gt;gas &amp;amp; building variables on the fly&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;writing data to storage is one of the most expensive things you can do on the blockchain, so in a lot of cases it makes sense to create things on the fly&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;in order to make sure your arrays stay in memory, use the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/code&gt; tag when you declare them&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;memory&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[][&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;uint&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;++&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  	&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;values&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also for loop look like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;erc271-crypto-collectibles&quot;&gt;ERC271, Crypto collectibles&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;tokens-on-ethereum&quot;&gt;Tokens on Ethereum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tokens are basically contracts that follow a standard set of rules&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;implements the same functions (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;transferFrom&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;balanceOf&lt;/code&gt;…)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have a standard, we can build on top of tokens more easily. For example, and exchange can work with any kind of ERC20 token&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have ERC20 tokens (similar to currencies) and ERC271 tokens (NFTs). NFTs are not interchangeable or divisible&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;erc271-standard-multiple-inheritance&quot;&gt;ERC271 standard, multiple inheritance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to make an NFT, we inherit from ERC271. This means we need to implement &lt;strong&gt;multiple inheritance&lt;/strong&gt; by using the following syntax:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-solidity highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;contract&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ChildClass&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ParentA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;ParentB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;transfer-logic&quot;&gt;Transfer Logic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have two different ways to transfer NFTs here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;transferFrom&lt;/strong&gt; - the owner transfers the NFT to the recipient&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;approve&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;transferFrom&lt;/strong&gt; - the owner approves a transfer to a specific address, then the recipient calls the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;transferFrom&lt;/code&gt; fununction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">source: CryptoZombies</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes: How Galileo Created the Problem of Consiousness</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notes/galileo-consiousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes: How Galileo Created the Problem of Consiousness" /><published>2021-12-19T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2021-12-19T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notes/playing-monogamy%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notes/galileo-consiousness/">&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/599229/galileos-error-by-philip-goff/&quot;&gt;Galileo’s Error&lt;/a&gt;, by Philip Goff (Chapter 1)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is about &lt;strong&gt;conscious experience&lt;/strong&gt;, and states that characterize our &lt;strong&gt;subjective inner lives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;experiences are what make life worth living&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it’s the only thing we know for sure is real&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rene Descarte - “Cogito ergo sum” (I think therefor I am)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but we have not incorporated it into our scientific picture of the world&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at this point, neuroscience hasn’t even started to explain it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;well-get-there-in-the-end&quot;&gt;We’ll get there in the end&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other branches of science (like biochemistry), we can focus on the answerable questions first. Then we might have the tools to get to the harder questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the real problem of consciousness&lt;/strong&gt;: mapping brain activity to conscious experience&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we should take this problem seriously&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we’ve started working on a theoretical framework to address the problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patricia Churchland&lt;/strong&gt; - neurophilosopher, “get out of the armchair and into the lab” proponent&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;eliminative materialism&lt;/strong&gt; the mind doesn’t exist and we shouldn’t try to explain it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thinks that complex functions of the mind (”thought”, “desire”) are outdated concepts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;thinks we should talk about human behavior in terms of electrochemical processes in the brain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science can tell us counterintuitive things about the world, but it &lt;strong&gt;can’t tell us we don’t have experiences&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-science&quot;&gt;What is Science?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science helps us reimagine nature&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;example: gravity is responsible for apples falling to the ground &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the orbit of the moon&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;example: space and time aren’t two distinct entities. They’re both spacetime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think of science as driven by experiments but thought experiments are powerful tools&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Einstein used thought experiments to identify gravitational force as the result of curvature in the fabric of spacetime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scientific revolution worked because it &lt;strong&gt;excluded consciousness from the domain of science&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;philosophical-foundations-of-science&quot;&gt;Philosophical Foundations of Science&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Galileo Galilei&lt;/strong&gt; (1564-1642) - father of modern science&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;declared that math is the language of science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aristotelian orthodoxy&lt;/strong&gt; acceptance of Aristotle’s worldview&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ptolemaic&lt;/strong&gt; view of the universe (earth at the center)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;teleological&lt;/strong&gt; theory (inanimate objects have goals)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all assume that Galileo disproved Aristotle’s view through scientific method, but he did it using a thought experiment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Galileo, philosophers thought the world was full of &lt;em&gt;sensory qualities.&lt;/em&gt; After, scientists thought of material objects as existing without sensory qualities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;example: lemons aren’t yellow. We perceive the yellowness in our souls&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;example: sound exists in the material world only as waves. It only exists as sound when we listen to it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Galileo divided the world into &lt;strong&gt;material objects&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;souls&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was meant to be a &lt;strong&gt;partial description of reality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;by narrowing the scope of inquiry, we’ve been able to achieve a lot using science&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that science as we know it might not solve the problem of consciousness&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-option-naturalistic-dualism&quot;&gt;First Option: Naturalistic Dualism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dualism&lt;/strong&gt; divides nature into two categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;physical objects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;incorporeal consciousness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;naturalistic dualism&lt;/strong&gt; says the mind is not magical, but it’s part of the natural order&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;second-option-materialism&quot;&gt;Second Option: Materialism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical materialists argue that consciousness is an illusion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;third-option-panpsychism&quot;&gt;Third Option: Panpsychism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Panpsychists believe that consciousness is a fundamental and ubiquitous feature of the physical world&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">source: Galileo’s Error, by Philip Goff (Chapter 1)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes: The Bad Guys Are Winning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notes/bad-guys-winning/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes: The Bad Guys Are Winning" /><published>2021-12-19T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2021-12-19T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notes/bad-guys-winning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notes/bad-guys-winning/">&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2021/12/the-autocrats-are-winning/620526/&quot;&gt;The Atlantic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;sviatlana-tsikhanouskaya&quot;&gt;Sviatlana Tsikhanouskaya&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably won the 2020 presidential election in &lt;strong&gt;Belarus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Immediately afterward, &lt;strong&gt;Alexander Lukashenko&lt;/strong&gt; forced her out of the country&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Her husband, &lt;strong&gt;Siarhei Tskhanouski&lt;/strong&gt;, is imprisoned in Belarus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-campaign&quot;&gt;the campaign&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Siarhei ran for president because he was &lt;strong&gt;frustrated with bureucracy and corruption&lt;/strong&gt;. The regime ended his campaign and imprisoned him. Sviatlana ran in his place&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the campaign was about ordinary people standing up to the regime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two prominent opposition polititions endorsed her campaign (their campaigns were blocked)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;She continued dispite death threats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;results-of-the-election&quot;&gt;Results of the election&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;officials announced that Lukashenko won 80% of the vote (no one believed this). Right afterward:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the internet was cut off&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sviatlana was detained by police and forced out of the country&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mass demonstrations across Belarus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sviatlana thought that the regime would give way to pressure, but it didn’t&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;sviatlana-in-the-eu&quot;&gt;Sviatlana in the EU&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;she wants to &lt;strong&gt;pressure the regime&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sanctions, democratic unity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;anything that makes it expensive for Lukashenko to stay in power&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She met with &lt;strong&gt;Merkel, Macron and Biden. They broadened sanctions&lt;/strong&gt; on Belarus&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stayed in Lithuania, which was proud to host her dispite the trouble at the Border&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She now has the entire free world backing her, but it’s not enough to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lukashenkos-rescue-package&quot;&gt;Lukashenko’s rescue package&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When protests first broke out after the election, he didn’t have a plan, but he got help from Moscow&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FSB: Russian security services&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;flew from Moscow to Minsk - helped Lukashenko quell the dissent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shift to a more sophisticated, more controlled way to repress the population&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Russian television journalists&lt;/strong&gt; replaced some Belarusian journalists&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;portrayed demonstrations as the work of America&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Russian police&lt;/strong&gt; supplemented Belarusian police&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mass arrests are unnecessary if you can jail, torture or murder the right people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Russian companies&lt;/strong&gt; offered markets for Belarusian products that had been banned in the democratic west&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rescue package was very similar to the one Putin sent Bashar al-Assad in Syria six years earlier&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-did-putin-do-this&quot;&gt;Why did Putin do this?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the Arab Spring (and the fall of the Berlin wall) made it clear that &lt;strong&gt;democratic revolutions are contagious&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;regime change means death, imprisonment or exile&lt;/strong&gt; in an authoritarian country&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Putin can influence Belarus to remain authoritarian, regime change in Russia is less likely&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lukashenkos-brazen--illegal-actions&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lukashenko’s&lt;/strong&gt; brazen &amp;amp; illegal actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;he’s active as if he was untouchable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In May 2021, Belarusian air traffic control &lt;strong&gt;forced an Irish passenger plane to land&lt;/strong&gt; in Minsk
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;this was in order to &lt;strong&gt;arrest Roman Protasevich&lt;/strong&gt;, a young exiled dissident&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In August, &lt;strong&gt;Vitaly Shishov was hanged&lt;/strong&gt; in Kyiv park&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lukashenko’s regime tried to destabalize its EU neighbors by &lt;strong&gt;forcing streams of refugees across their borders&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;lured&lt;/strong&gt; Afghan and Iraqi &lt;strong&gt;refugees to Minsk&lt;/strong&gt; with tourist visas&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forced them across the borders&lt;/strong&gt; of Lithuania, Latvia and Poland &lt;strong&gt;at gunpoint&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;networks-of-despots&quot;&gt;Networks of despots&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modern autocracies&lt;/strong&gt; are not run by one bad guy. They’re &lt;strong&gt;run by sophisticated networks&lt;/strong&gt; of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;kleptocratic financial structures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;security services (police, surveillance, military)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;propagandists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These networks are often &lt;strong&gt;international and do not have a unifying ideology.&lt;/strong&gt; There is no leader and they’re connected by economic deals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this eases the pressure sanctions and makes everyone rich&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, Belarus is an international pariah. In practice, it’s a member of Autocracy Inc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China&lt;/strong&gt; is working on a large development project there&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iran&lt;/strong&gt; has expanded its relationship with Belarus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cuba&lt;/strong&gt;n officials have called for an end to “foreign interference”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Venezuela&lt;/strong&gt; is in a similar position. The United States, Canada, the EU and many of its neighbors have &lt;strong&gt;sanctions&lt;/strong&gt; against it. &lt;strong&gt;Millions of people protest&lt;/strong&gt; in the streets&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Russia and China&lt;/strong&gt; invest in Marudo’s Regime&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turkey&lt;/strong&gt; helps with an illicit gold trade&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cuba&lt;/strong&gt; provides security advisors and technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If Venezuela’s regime were acting alone, it would fall&lt;/strong&gt;, but it’s receiving &lt;strong&gt;help from other autocracies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impervious-to-criticism&quot;&gt;Impervious to Criticism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leaders of the Soviet Union cared deeply about how the world perceived them, but today &lt;strong&gt;autocracies don’t care about criticism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this enables them to use aggressive tactics against mass protests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the &lt;strong&gt;Maduro Model&lt;/strong&gt; of governence means that autocrats are willing to pay the price of becoming a totally failed country&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;means economic collaps, isolation and mass poverty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;but the autocrat stays in power&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;might be what’s in store for Belarus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The west won’t provide money, so they depend on China, Pakistan, Russia and Saudi Arabia&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might explain the &lt;strong&gt;pathetic reaction to the fall of Kabul&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;uyghurs&quot;&gt;Uyghurs&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;50,000 exiled Uyghers live in Turkey. In another era, these exiles would have sympathy from the Turkish government&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in 2009, &lt;strong&gt;Erdogan called Chinese repression of Uyghurs a genocide&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He has strengthened ties with China since becoming president&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;recently, the Turkish government has surveilled and detained Uyghurs on bogus terrorism charges. Deported some to China&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late 2020, a delayed shipment of covid vaccines from China looked suspiciously like a ransom for Uyghur extridition, even though both governments deny it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;surprisingly-muslim-countries-are-turning-a-blind-eye-to-uyghurs-in-china&quot;&gt;Surprisingly, Muslim countries are turning a blind eye to Uyghurs in China&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pakistani Primi Minister accepts the Chinese version of events&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudis, Emiratis and Egyptians have all arrested and deported Uyghurs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all these countries have purchased Chinese surveillance technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s as if these countries agree to accept China’s action on Hong Kong, Tibet, Uygurs and human rights in exchange for investment and equipment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;it-happened-here&quot;&gt;It happened here&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t learn much after 2016 Russian election interference&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-united-front&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The United Front&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;an influence projet for the CCP. Meant to shape global opinion about china&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;faculty in American universities tried to shape academic debates in China’s favor. This was in the context of calligraphy courses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese democracy activists &lt;em&gt;in America&lt;/em&gt; are harrased by Chinese agents&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some have had strange car accidents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;american-industry&quot;&gt;American Industry&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;lots of personal, financial, business links to China and Russia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hollywood and sports appeal to CCP&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;liberal-democracy-vs-authoritarianism-around-the-world&quot;&gt;Liberal Democracy vs Authoritarianism around the world&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Srdja Popovic&lt;/strong&gt; democracy activist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;says democratic movements are becoming better organized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;were-not-doing-too-well&quot;&gt;We’re not doing too well&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diplomatic tools we used to use against autocrats don’t work anymore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sanctions don’t have the same impact&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Democracy assistance&lt;/strong&gt; America spends money on this, but it’s not a lot in comparison to what the Authoritarian leaders will spend&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We still have American foreign-language broadcasters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Russia spends billions on state media, seen all over Europe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China spends billions on media globally&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t have an answer to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the silk road initiative&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the United Front&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Russian disinformation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;actions-to-take-today&quot;&gt;Actions to take today&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biden hosted a &lt;strong&gt;summit for democracy&lt;/strong&gt; Dec 9-10 (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/graphic-detail/2021/12/06/joe-bidens-summit-for-democracy-is-not-all-that-democratic&quot;&gt;The Economist focused more on who was invited than the content&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;means very little&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real actions we should take:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shut down tax havens, enforce money-laundering laws&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stop selling surveillance tech to autocracies&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Divest from vicious regimes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;figure out how to respond when autocracies commit crimes outside their borders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-americas-doing-now&quot;&gt;How America’s doing now&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our actions on the global stage have been declining. So has global respect for American democracy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trump&lt;/strong&gt; seems okay with global autocracy, and he eroded rules and norms that strengthen democracy in the United States&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The American left&lt;/strong&gt; has become dissolusioned with democracy at home&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;focused on America’s problems, convinced that democracy doesn’t work, or that it’s not working here&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When protesters in Hong Kong asked for help, American activists didn’t do much&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">source: The Atlantic</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes: The Spanish Civil War</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notes/spanish-civil-war/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes: The Spanish Civil War" /><published>2021-10-28T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2021-10-28T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notes/spanish-civil-war</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notes/spanish-civil-war/">&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.veryshortintroductions.com/view/10.1093/actrade/9780192803771.001.0001/actrade-9780192803771&quot;&gt;The Spanish Civil War: A Very Short Introduction&lt;/a&gt;, Helen Graham&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The civil war started with a coup on July 17-18th, 1936&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-origins&quot;&gt;1: Origins&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three crucial factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were &lt;strong&gt;extremely uneven levels of development&lt;/strong&gt; within Spain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the &lt;strong&gt;cultural influence of Catholicism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spain’s army&lt;/strong&gt; had an intolerant political culture in its officer corps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditional order was coming under strain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1923: soft military coup by General Miguel Primo de Rivera (had backing of the king)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1930: army opposition brought Primo down&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1931: republic was declared peacefully&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;uneven-levels-of-development&quot;&gt;Uneven Levels of Development&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a debate over how Spain should modernize itself economically&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WWI caused social change - economic boom, severe inflation and dislocation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Political parties were illegal in the 1920s, so professional associations became more powerful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;progressive industrial elites (based in Catalan textile sector)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;large landowners in souther half of Spain&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;It was similar to the American deep south - landless peasants lived like slaves&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;urban professional sector &amp;amp; industrial workers - wanted political voice&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CNT: anarcho-syndicalist trade union movement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;catholicism&quot;&gt;Catholicism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;embraced order and hierarchy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;church’s monopoly on truth was challenged by political liberalism and cultural pluralism&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;local priests were allies of landowners and souther police - &lt;strong&gt;made rural poor anticlerical&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catholics didn’t like being constrained, but had no tolerance for non-catholics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spains-army&quot;&gt;Spain’s Army&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spain lost its empire in 1898 - deprived the over-large officer corps of any meaningful external role&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;powerful myth that civilian politicians had been responsible for the final loss of empire&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;disliked metropolitan Spanish society and politics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;took charge of Spain’s main military academy at Zaragoza&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spain’s military class was becoming increasingly isolated&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Junior officers stood to lose a lot of money from the Republican reforms&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;large-southern-landowners&quot;&gt;Large Southern Landowners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;used religious issues to mobilize poor northern smallholders to act against their own interests&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;franco&quot;&gt;Franco&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;entered the military academy in 1907 (at the age of 15)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made his career in the colonial Army of Africa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;progressive-republicans-in-power&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progressive Republicans in Power&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coalition of socially progressive Republicans and Socialists&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Republicans wanted social reform: land ownership, education, state-church relations, the army&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Socialists wanted welfare&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The coalition was less effective because of big ideological differences between republicans and socialists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Republican Reforms were designed to increase &lt;strong&gt;economic democracy,&lt;/strong&gt; which is a &lt;strong&gt;prerequisite for political democracy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agrarian reform&lt;/strong&gt; intended to create smallholding peasantry in souther Spain. They’d be loyal to repluclicans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;separation of church and state&lt;/strong&gt; - no more subsidy to clergy (alienated many poor priests)
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;unpopular interference with Catholic culture&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;opposition to women’s suffrage. Thought women would be influenced by the church&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;secularization was impolitic, ill thought-out and counterproductive&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;education&lt;/strong&gt; - more money to non-religious primary education&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;army reform&lt;/strong&gt; - to bring the army under civilian and constitutional control
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tried to close down military academy at Zaragoza, enraging &lt;em&gt;Africanistas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These reforms were extremely ambitious&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;too many at once&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;attempted during a depression&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;opposed by Spain’s traditional elites (landowners, church, millitary)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their reforms made them enemies, but never actually went into affect&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-rebellion&quot;&gt;2: Rebellion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The coup began on July 17th, 1936&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;started in Spanish North Africa (Morocco)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;spread to mainland Spain the next day (provincial garrison revolts)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;one result was the government in Madrid didn’t have a functioning army&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trade unions and political parties had to find an army&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;used a combination of the (loyal) police and the worker militia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quelled the urban garrison revolts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Republican/progressive areas tended to be areas where the rebellion didn’t take hold&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Catalonia and Valencia stayed Republican throughout the war&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Madrid was the capital of the Republic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No area of Spain was entirely conservative&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people with Republican sympathies in conservative areas had to publicly embrace the rebellion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;often led to betrayals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week after the initial coup, the rebels got planes from Hitler and Mussolini&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;used to transport their troops to Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government didn’t have power outside of Madrid&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people used the chaos to settle personal vendettas (post-coup violence and pre-war conflicts)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lots of violence against the powerful. Priests and monks were killed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the violence damaged the Republic’s credibility abroad when it needed external support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violence in rebel areas: goal was purification&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;local civilian elites declared this&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;fascists saw killings as cleansing the community of pollution&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this applied to anyone who benefited from the Republic, whether they were political or not: teachers and intellectuals, “new” women, self-educated workers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;at first, vigilantes killed people. However, these vigilantes usually either had close links to rightist organizations, or they were working with the authorities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meant that there was killing on both sides, but there was an asymmetry to it: the republicans didn’t have the ability to stop the violence. The rebels did, but they chose not to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For rebels, liberal politics were the problem, and the solution was terror&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it undid the Republic’s redistribution of social and economic power&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it created a complicity between the rebel authorities and everyone who turned against their friends &amp;amp; family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Home was no longer safe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people migrated back home after the coup, but their former neighbors killed them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Francisco Franco&lt;/strong&gt; headed &lt;strong&gt;The Army of Africa&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Army of Africa moved through the souther half of Spain, large landowners reclaimed their land. They killed Rural laborers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This warfare was similar to colonial campaigns agains insubordinate indigenous peoples&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They faced a local civilian population with no real weapons, so they tore through the southern half of Spain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spain had used poison gas against people in Morocco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franco’s political belief was that alien political ideas had &lt;em&gt;occupied&lt;/em&gt; Spain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I will save Spain from Marxism whatever the cost” “And if that means shooting half of Spain” “As I said, whatever the cost”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Catholic Church provided legitimacy to the rebels, so they got very little bad press abroad&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Spanish left cared more about workers’ rights than the wrongs of colonization&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Emilio Mola&lt;/strong&gt; nominal leader of the rebellion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-the-republic-at-war&quot;&gt;3: The Republic at War&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-Intervention treaty&lt;/strong&gt; (August 1936) that Britain and France signed with Germany and Italy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;said they wouldn’t deliver war material to Spain&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Britain and France honored it. Germany and Italy didn’t&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This gave the rebels a huge advantage over the republic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did Britain &amp;amp; France allow this to happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Idea was to prevent Spanish war from escalating into a European conflict&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also, the British thought that a rebel victory would preserve more capital, which affected British investments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Also&lt;/em&gt;, Britain’s governing elite had political, personal and financial connections to conservative Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain and France were screwing the republic over&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; Germany and Italy were not honoring the treaty, but they didn’t do anything about it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Britain refused the republic’s navy the right to review in Gibraltar or Tangier&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;France reneged on its initial promise to send war material&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitler and Mussolini’s aid was strategically motivated, although ideology also played apart&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Soviet Union provisioned military aid in &lt;strong&gt;November 1936.&lt;/strong&gt; This aid was just in time&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;At first, the Soviets backed Non-Intervention&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They thought the Republic would win under these circumstances if the fascists honored the agreement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The soviets never acknowledged the military assistance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;anti-fascists-came-to-spain-to-fight&quot;&gt;anti-fascists came to Spain to fight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;International Brigrades&lt;/strong&gt; (about 35,000)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most were already political exiles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a quarter of the volunteers were Jewish - were actively anti-fascist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Example: Canadian volunteers who had fled Finland’s nationalist leader around 1918&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The brigades were diverse, which made them antithetical to the fascist ideals of purification&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;brigades were used as shock troops and sustained high casualties&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Abraham Lincoln Brigade&lt;/strong&gt; included 90 black Americans
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oliver Law -&lt;/strong&gt; first military commander in US history to lead a nonsegregated unit of troops&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foreign medical volunteers joined too&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developed new types of emergency treatment, like blood transfusion techniques&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Women generally weren’t recruited to help fight&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The European communist movement organized most of the international brigades and lobbied governments to lift non-intervention&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comintern (Communist International)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PCF (French Communist Party)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Republican military command were hostile to the international brigades&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;because reasons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volunteers weren’t prepared for the war&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;military discipline&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;harsh warfare&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;antiquated weaponry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conditions-in-madrid&quot;&gt;Conditions in Madrid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the first &lt;strong&gt;air raids&lt;/strong&gt; of their kind to happen anywhere in Europe&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;War Refugees&lt;/strong&gt; first went to Madrid, then Barcelona and Valencia - severe culture shock&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rebel army &lt;strong&gt;besieged&lt;/strong&gt; Madrid&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fascist-help&quot;&gt;Fascist Help&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitler and Mussolini recognized rebel Spain in November 1936, provided weaponry and manpower (75,000 troops)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;internal-fighting&quot;&gt;Internal fighting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Republic distrusted their professional army officers, and the coup had shattered &lt;strong&gt;army unity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were political tensions between &lt;strong&gt;the center and periphery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the &lt;strong&gt;central Republican government&lt;/strong&gt; clashed with the &lt;strong&gt;Basque regional authority&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PNV (Basque Nationalist Party)&lt;/strong&gt; sought sovereign rights&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the war, there had already been political rivalries between different groups&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the war intensified them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clashes between socialists-led trade unions, communists and Catalan communists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;basque-fell-in-the-summer-of-1937&quot;&gt;Basque fell in the summer of 1937&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this happened just as the republican military was beginning to cohere&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;also guerrilla fighters behind enemy lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;republics-propaganda&quot;&gt;Republic’s Propaganda&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;used &lt;strong&gt;photomontage&lt;/strong&gt; as a weapon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;depicted their own soldiers as mechanized and modernist&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the fascists didn’t do this because &lt;strong&gt;photomontage was modernist and cosmopolitan&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cultural-bolshevism&quot;&gt;Cultural Bolshevism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the Nazis coined this term to describe &lt;strong&gt;avant-garde cultural production&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;degenerate art&lt;/strong&gt; - Nazi Germany’s term for modern art&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;idea that a culture can degenerate like a biological organism was widespread, especially among conservative sectors in Europe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soviet fashion became popular&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the styles were superficial and had little to do with Marxist-Leninism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wartime-madrid&quot;&gt;Wartime Madrid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government tried to centralize power&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;local governments and trade unions had gained more power since the war had started&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government re-introduced market forces to the food supply&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this hit the urban poor the hardest. They couldn’t afford the black market and they had no contacts in the countryside&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Housing shortage&lt;/strong&gt; - 350,000 refugees by the end of 1936 meant a 10% population increase&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;extra pressure on housing and food in the poorest inner city areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May Days&lt;/strong&gt; - period of time where [radicalized workers and the urban poor] staged [social and political protests] in Barcelona&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;these caused sectarian political struggles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Soviet intelligence was involved somehow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Italian secret police assassinated an Italian anarchist in Barcelona during this time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrue Nin&lt;/strong&gt; - leader of Catalan-based dissent party&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spanish/Catalan communists worked with the Comintern to assassinate hime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Checas&lt;/strong&gt; - illegal prisons, appeared in Republican territory in the aftermath of the military uprising&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;political parties, unions and militia established their on detention agencies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It became more common to incorporate women and young people into the war effort&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this was partly due the the increased popularity of the Soviet Union&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-rebel-spain&quot;&gt;4: Rebel Spain&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Francoist Spain was much more ideologically homogeneous&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;franco-1&quot;&gt;Franco&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People in power died by accident or got executed by the rebels. Also &lt;strong&gt;Franco had control of the Army of Africa&lt;/strong&gt; at the beginning of the war&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franco’s mission was to “save Spain”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this shaped his military strategy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;he probably thought he was justified in terrorizing civilians&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franco’s military strategy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;colonize the metropolis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;destroy the “alien” republican culture in the cities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;purify Spain from everything that didn’t align with his values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franco thought that industrial cities caused moral pollution&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The war was more about controlling people than about controlling territory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Franco was prepared to incur losses among his troops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franco thought that the Army had an absolute right to impose its will on society&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thought that military organization was the best way to structure a society&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franco deported Spanish Republicans to Nazi concentration camps in 1940&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wartime-stuff&quot;&gt;Wartime stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Estado Campamental&lt;/strong&gt; - “Battlefield state”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;By mobilizing Spain’s armies, Franco was achieving the “ideal Spain”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rebels used a lot of air raides&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they backfired. Caused more hatred than fear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Falange&lt;/strong&gt; - a group&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;leader got executed by Republicans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blue Division&lt;/strong&gt; fought with the German armies on the eastern front (1941)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;old shirt Falangists joined this&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seccion Femenina (SF)&lt;/strong&gt; - women’s section of the Falange. An “army” of unmarried, economically independent women&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Urban and provincial middle class women joined this&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Women were mobilized for health and welfare needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not used for industrial war work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;valued domesticity and subservience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anti-Comintern pact&lt;/strong&gt; - (February 1939) agreement between Germany, Japan and Italy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;after-the-victory&quot;&gt;After the victory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spaniards had to &lt;strong&gt;denounce&lt;/strong&gt; their neighbors to military tribunals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this happened after Franco’s military victory in April 1936&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government took all the wealth and property by passing legislation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;captured-republican-soldiers&quot;&gt;Captured Republican Soldiers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;they were often recycled&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;especially the ones who had been conscripts in the first place&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;after the war, they faced political investigation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political commissars&lt;/strong&gt; were usually shot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;international brigaders&lt;/strong&gt; were usually shot&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meant that Franco was breaking the Geneva Conventions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;propoganda&quot;&gt;Propoganda&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commercial cinema was becoming more popular&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Francoist authorities censored them carefully&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hollywood productions were an important component of popular cinema&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;help-from-germany-and-italy&quot;&gt;Help from Germany and Italy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hitler and Mussolini wanted a fast victory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They increased their aid for this outcome&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Franco advanced his army slowly and deliberately&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This caused political tension&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franco depended heavily on Italian military hardware&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Germany and Italy provided airpower, and Franco needed it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why did this alliance happen?&lt;/strong&gt; All three dictators wanted to expand their territories&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they would turn a blind eye to each other’s imperial actions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nazi Germany was disrupting the international status quo, which meant more opportunities to gain territory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spain would disrupt French and English imperial interests, since it was in an important strategic position&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was an ideological divide between Francoists and Nazis over the Catholic church&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Nazis were trying to take society beyond sectarian allegiances&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;passive-france-and-britain&quot;&gt;Passive France and Britain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;British government didn’t think that a Francoist victory would pose a threat to their interests. They didn’t help much&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-church&quot;&gt;The Church&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the Vatican didn’t like the radical aspects of fascism, or its exaltation of the state&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;opposed Nazism for its atheistic dimension&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this is why the Vatican publicly condemned Hitler’s racism&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This was very bad for Franco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vatican attempted to broker peace settlements with Franco&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vatican established full diplomatic relations in 1938, when a rebel victory seemed imminent&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spain’s Catholic hierarchy&lt;/strong&gt; aligned itself with Franco&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shared hostility with rationalism, liberalism, socialism and communism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franco’s government would mix in fascist symbols during ceremonial occasions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-the-republic-besieged&quot;&gt;5: The Republic besieged&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rebels were way better equipped than the Republic&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Portuguese authorities unloaded German and Italian supplies at their ports&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;most of the middle-ranking officers were on Franco’s side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stalin sent materiel to the republic (including planes and tanks)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This was crucial for their survival&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Non-Intervention prevented the Republic from buying war material on its own behalf&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this is a big reason why it needed Soviet help&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Republic also didn’t have access to its money&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the outgoing cabinet transferred Spain’s gold reserves out of the country right before the war (two weeks after the coup)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mexico was the only country that helped the Republic as a broker&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eastern European countries (mainly Poland) sold armaments to the Republic&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Republic had to overpay for everything because of Non-Intervention&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Had to pay cash up front (unlike the rebels, which bought everything on credit)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;delivery-was-a-nightmare&quot;&gt;Delivery was a nightmare&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Soviets made the Republic transport everything they bought&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Germans and Italians illegally attacked all ships bound for Republic ports&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They allowed Franco to set up a blockade&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;french-help&quot;&gt;French help&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The blockade meant that all military aid had to go over land, through France&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The French were afraid of being surrounded by fascists, so they practiced “relaxed Non-Intervention”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;goods could go over the French border to Spain, but this route was unpredictable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-fractured-republic&quot;&gt;A Fractured Republic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were “five armies, not one”, mainly due to regional groupings&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During 1938, the Republican camp had many political divisions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the more defeats it suffered, the more divisions there were&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;central Republican versus the regional government of Catalonia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catalonia had one of the deepest independent political and cultural traditions in Spain. When &lt;strong&gt;Negrin assumed control of the Catalan war industry&lt;/strong&gt;, he caused another fracture&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-fall-of-asturias&quot;&gt;The Fall of Asturias&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October 1937 - made it clear that the Republic wouldn’t win&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no more coal industry&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;no more northern army (200k soldiers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;battle-of-teruel&quot;&gt;Battle of Teruel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;winter 1937-8 - made it even more clear that the Republic wouldn’t win&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;was a diversionary campaign&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that was an especially cold winter&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Republicans captured the city in January, but Franco got it back in a counter offensive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clear turning point of the war&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Franco captured the city, 15k prisoners and lots of military equipment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-rebels-took-vinaros&quot;&gt;The rebels took Vinaros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rebels separated Catalonia from the central-south Republican zone&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this was &lt;em&gt;very bad&lt;/em&gt; for the Republic, but Franco diverted troops south to Valencia because he thought that France would have to intervene if he sent troops to Catalonia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The point was to attack the Republic’s human resources as much as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;anglo-italian-agreement&quot;&gt;Anglo-Italian agreement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;April 1938 Britain signed this right after the rebels took a significant victory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain pressured France to close its frontier to Spain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Italy was still sinking Britain’s merchant ships, so this didn’t make much sense&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;soviet-help&quot;&gt;Soviet help&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soviet technical advisors (about 700 of them) helped Spanish commanders and officers&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;military engineers, technicians, strategists and experts in irregular warfare&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By 1938, Stalin thought that the Republic couldn’t win, so he stopped helping in any significant way&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there were foreign volunteers, but they were basically symbolic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The longer the Republic resisted, the longer it distracted Germany, so Stalin did continue to help&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;internal-fracturing&quot;&gt;Internal Fracturing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Negrin did the following, he damaged morale in Catalonia:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move the Republican government to Barcelona&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;assumed direct control of Catalan war industry&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catalonia had the deepest independent political and cultural traditions in Spain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;socialists-vs-communists&quot;&gt;socialists vs communists&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;these were the two mass movements sustaining the war effort&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;had rivalies before the war that grew more intense during the war&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;juan-negrin&quot;&gt;Juan Negrin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Republican prime minister, took office in May 1937&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tried to get Non-Intervention lifted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;good at international diplomacy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Non-Intervention basically ended when Hitler occupied Austria in March 1938, but it was too late by then&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;values&quot;&gt;Values&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negrin prioritized Republican morale, tried to strengthen Spain’s constitutional order&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed his wartime measures to reinforce &lt;strong&gt;liberal market-based values&lt;/strong&gt;, instead of collectivist or anti-capitalist values&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wanted to &lt;strong&gt;normalize the Catholic Church&lt;/strong&gt;, even though he was a secular rationalist&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;wanted to reintroduce public worship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The communist ideology did not appeal to him&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;actions-aborad&quot;&gt;Actions Aborad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain and France were afraid of the conflict extending to the rest of Europe, so &lt;strong&gt;they opposed Negrin’s bid to have Non-Intervention lifted&lt;/strong&gt; at the league of Nations&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negrin made a number of trips abroad in 1938 to meet with fascists&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;he wanted to prevent reprisals and guarantee the integrity of Spain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;politics-at-home&quot;&gt;Politics at home&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negrin was starting to rely on the communists more than on his own party, which caused problems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;He needed the communists because of their &lt;strong&gt;commitment to a policy of resistance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;downfall&quot;&gt;Downfall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By spring 1938, the Republic couldn’t serve its civilian population effectively&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;catalonia-isolated&quot;&gt;Catalonia Isolated&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communication between Catalonia and the central zone was hazardous&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was difficult to travel there, since the rebels controlled sea and air between the two zones&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rebels torpedoed sea traffic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food had to come from France, but there wasn’t enough food coming across the border. Also, whether it came at all depended on politics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;militarization&quot;&gt;Militarization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Republican zone was militarizing under the pressure of war, which backfired&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;conscription was becoming more aggressive, which made communities resentful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;soldiers were living off the land, which increased social tension&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-fifth-column&quot;&gt;The fifth column&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All major Republican cities had organized networks of spies and saboteurs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it was difficult for the Republic to deal with these spies without resorting to fascistic surveillance and interrogation techniques&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this contrasted with how the Francoists dealth with spies, which gave the fascists an advantage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Played a major role in the eventual hand over to Franco&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;battle-at-ebro&quot;&gt;Battle at Ebro&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;July - November 1938. The last big battle during the war&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Republic’s last gamble&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;three objectives:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;protect Valencia from Franco&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;restore contact with Catalonia&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;demonstrate to the world that the Republican army was resilient (success - the Brits noticed the victory, and noticed how reliant Franco was on Italy and Germany)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Franco paid the Nazi’s in mining rights. In exchange, they guaranteed his air superiority during the battle at Ebro&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This was a testing ground for Blitzkrieg tactics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;also for Soviet armored vehicles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the republicans retreated in November because of the Munich agreement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-agreement&quot;&gt;The agreement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Britain and France signed a deal with Germany and Italy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It said that Hitler could invade Czechoslovakia&lt;/strong&gt;, which was the last functioning democracy in central eastern Europe&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this undermined Negrin’s credibility and his resistance strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;poum-trial&quot;&gt;POUM Trial&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;October 1938 (so duing the battle of Ebro) - POUM leaders publicly supported a rebellion&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the trial observed the constitutional process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-downfall&quot;&gt;The downfall&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negrin knew that if he surrendured, Franco would not negotiate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;he planned on resisting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Las of Political Responsibilities&lt;/strong&gt; law pushed by Franco in February 1939&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;blanket repression, meant that there would be reprisals against Republican population&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;retroactively punished people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other republican and socialist leaders thought that they could negotiate pease with Franco, even though it was clear they couldn’t&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Armies surrendured to Franco in &lt;strong&gt;March 1939&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Negrin had continued resisting because he believed that Britain and France would help Republican Spain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;refugees&quot;&gt;Refugees&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were about 600k refugees trying to escape from Republican Spain at the end of the war&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">source: The Spanish Civil War: A Very Short Introduction, Helen Graham</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes: Genetics and Politics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notes/genetics-politics/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes: Genetics and Politics" /><published>2021-09-26T04:07:43+08:00</published><updated>2021-09-26T04:07:43+08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notes/genetics-politics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notes/genetics-politics/">&lt;p&gt;source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/09/13/can-progressives-be-convinced-that-genetics-matters&quot;&gt;The New Yorker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kathryn Paige Harden&lt;/strong&gt; works in the field of behavior genetics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;psych professor, University of Texas at Austin&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mentored by Eric Turkheimer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;behavior genetics&lt;/strong&gt; investigates influence of genes on &lt;strong&gt;character traits&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;life outcomes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pushback-from-hardens-colleagues&quot;&gt;pushback from Harden’s colleagues&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;there’s a possible link between behavior genetics and eugenics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harden was ostracized by her liberal colleagues for her work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;polygenic score&lt;/strong&gt; a weighted sum of an individuals relevant genetic variants&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harden shared &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0956797616643070&quot;&gt;a paper&lt;/a&gt; that used polygenic score to explain population variance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the paper emphasized that it’s difficult to distinguish between genetic and environmental effects on social outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was a lot of pushback to this paper. professor of public policy at Duke: “there will be no reason to pursue these types of research programs at all, and they can be rendered to the same location as Holocaust denial research”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Bell Curve&lt;/strong&gt;, Charles Murray &amp;amp; Richard Herrnstein - includes claims about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;genetic basis for racial hierarchy in intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;genetic foundation for poverty and inequality&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harden’s colleagues compared the paper she shared to the bell curve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;they considered refusing to fund research into effects of genes on behavior or social outcomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can’t commit to egalitarianism by declaring genetic uniformity&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The left isn’t talking about this, so the only voices are on the right&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“red pill” claims to expose liberal hypocrisy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harden is trying to fight back&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Genetic Lottery: Why DNA Matters for Social Equality&lt;/strong&gt; - Harden’s new book&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;behavioralism-vs-determinism&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;behavioralism vs determinism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;behavioralism&lt;/strong&gt; - claims that environmental manipulation can produce any desired outcome&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aligns with postwar liberal principles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/How_Much_Can_We_Boost_IQ_and_Scholastic_Achievement%3F&quot;&gt;How Much Can We Boost IQ and Scholastic Achievement?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - 1969 article&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;argued that there was an IQ gap between races in America, and the reason was at least partly genetic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;argued that policy interventions were unlikely shift this hierarchy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Got a lot of criticism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IQ is flexible&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poor children gain IQ after wealthy families adopt them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;populations gain IQ over time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because outcomes are partly genetic doesn’t mean they’re inevitable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/iq/1997-turkheimer.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Search for a Psychometric left&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Terkheimer argued that the left has nothing to fear from genes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We don’t need to deny heritability to oppose determinism, reductionism and racism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-limits-of-behavior-genetics&quot;&gt;the limits of behavior genetics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some studies found genes for aggression, depression, homosexuality, but &lt;strong&gt;the studies couldn’t be replicated&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complex traits are governed by multiple genes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;genome-wide association study&lt;/strong&gt; (GWAS)- attempt to identify thousands of places in the genome where DNA differences correlate to traits/outcomes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can predict population variance for height, weight and some diseases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;can predict some complex behavioral traits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A GWA for educational attainment found ~1300 sites on the genome that correlate with scholastic success&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;individual sites have a negligible predictive ability, but the sum is very predictive&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;people with the highest scores are 5x more likely to graduate from college&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GWAS show correlation, but not causation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;depend on populations within a specific society&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;results are not portable - results from the UK will not tell you anything about populations in Estonia&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not a good predictor for individuals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GWAS reveal a lot much about geography and culture&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;example: you could conduct a GWAS for chopstick use. It would tell you more about culture than individual’s dexterity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;possible solution: compare GWAS results within families&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social outcomes also depend on plenty of factors (conscientiousness, risk-aversion, physical features…)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Harden thinks we’ll be stuck forever if we consider this question to have a binary answer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One benefit of GWAS: they help you account for genetic differences when trying to do studies on environmental factors&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Parents have significant impact on environmental effects, even if they don’t pass on all of their genes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another benefit: We can see how treatments interact with genetics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;clash-with-sam-harris&quot;&gt;Clash with Sam Harris&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam Harris had Charles Murray on as a guest in April 2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they said that people don’t want to hear that IQ differs across ethnic groups&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harris mostly had him on because he’d been caught up in the culture war&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harden and Turkheimer wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/the-big-idea/2017/5/18/15655638/charles-murray-race-iq-sam-harris-science-free-speech&quot;&gt;piece for vox&lt;/a&gt; meant to confront Harris’ podcast&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They had to make a nuanced argument to separate the truths from the falsehoods in the podcast&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We can’t deny that genetics have an impact on human academic scores&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;However there’s &lt;strong&gt;no reason to think that racial IQ gaps are anything but the result of racism&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harris eventually had Harden on his podcast. It was actually pretty awkward&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;blowback-from-the-left&quot;&gt;blowback from the left&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more voices on the left that are trying to acknowledge inherited intelligence&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the cult of smart&lt;/strong&gt; asserts that improving the education system won’t help until we acknowledge that some students are just smarter than others&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harden is getting dragged on twitter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dorothy Roberts&lt;/strong&gt; professor of law, sociology, Africana studies - responded to a 2018 Op-Ed that Harden wrote in the NYT, which said we should use genetics to inform education policy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There’s no way that genetic testing is going to lead to a restructuring of society in a just way in the future. &lt;strong&gt;We have a hundred years of evidence for what happens when social outcomes are attributed to genetic differences&lt;/strong&gt;, and it is always to stigmatize, control and punish the people predicted to have socially devalued traits”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a push from the right to pay more attention to genetics&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;blueprint says that polygenic scores should be understood as “fortune tellers”, and white supremacists love it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-genetic-lottery&quot;&gt;The genetic lottery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;assersions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;just because we value some traits more than others doesn’t mean we value some people more than others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should view inherent qualities as something you were lucky to get&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We should get better at separating the questions of nature and nurture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we don’t acknowledge how genes played a part in our success, we assume that we did it all through hard work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If genes play a significant role in our success, maybe we shouldn’t design our society so that you need a college degree to get health care&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">source: The New Yorker</summary></entry></feed>